<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-09-22T03:45:42+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Data Strategy by Edafe Onerhime</title><subtitle>Learn how a data strategy can transform your business, provide value to customers, build trust and loyalty, boost productivity, and generate more revenue.</subtitle><author><name>ekoner</name></author><entry xml:lang="eng_GB"><title type="html">How big data changed and what this means for your business</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/09/20/how-big-data-changed-and-what-this-means-for-your-business.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How big data changed and what this means for your business" /><published>2019-09-20T09:49:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-09-20T09:49:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/09/20/how-big-data-changed-and-what-this-means-for-your-business</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/09/20/how-big-data-changed-and-what-this-means-for-your-business.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/headers/header-black-man-shaving-min.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/headers/header-black-man-shaving-min.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Big data: Will more Vs give you a closer shave?&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Big data: Will more Vs give you a closer shave?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, &lt;strong&gt;big data&lt;/strong&gt; was everywhere. Big data is data too big, complex or changing too fast to process in everyday software. Here I explore how big data has changed and what it can do for your business today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defining big data was always tricky. We started with three Vs: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gartner.com/it-glossary/big-data/&quot;&gt;Volume, Velocity and Variety&lt;/a&gt; . When the concept of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/gilpress/2013/05/09/a-very-short-history-of-big-data/#785805f865a1&quot;&gt;big data was first coined in 1999&lt;/a&gt;, it was data too large for mere mortal computing. It changed faster than Clark Kent to Superman in a phone booth. It was more amorphous than a bag of jelly. Big data would lead to big money and &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2a4jIZi&quot;&gt;a revolution that would transform how we live, work and think&lt;/a&gt;. And so, the hype geared up and big data became a phenomenon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/others/gartner-hype-cycle-big-data-2013-min.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/others/gartner-hype-cycle-big-data-2013-min.png&quot; alt=&quot;Disillusionment of Big Data&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image: © Gartner&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://knowledgeimmersion.wordpress.com/2016/06/22/disillusionment-of-big-data/&quot;&gt;Disillusionment of Big Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was soon clear that three Vs wouldn’t cut it. Like Gillette, the well known razor company, big data needed more Vs for better performance. From a single cut-throat razor, Gillette gave us the multi-bladed Mach 3 and Fusion, more blades for a closer shave. Big data followed, perhaps unknowingly in these footsteps. Soon there were four: meet &lt;strong&gt;Veracity&lt;/strong&gt;. It was no longer enough to be big, fast changing and complex, big data had to be credible too. After all,  &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garbage_in,_garbage_out&quot;&gt;garbage in means garbage out&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like any well fuelled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gartner.com/doc/2814517/hype-cycle-big-data-&quot;&gt;hype cycle&lt;/a&gt;, big data was peaking, but was it fulfilling the promise &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2agWknJ&quot;&gt;to make better decisions and improve performance?&lt;/a&gt;  It was big, fast changing, complex and now credible. Launching a big data project showed your organisation had its finger on the pulse of technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But what could big data actually do for you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just launching a big data project didn’t make it useful, so a fifth V joined the list: &lt;strong&gt;Value&lt;/strong&gt; (your mileage may vary, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wired.com/2013/05/the-missing-vs-in-big-data-viability-and-value/&quot;&gt;viability&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.softwareinsider.org/2012/02/27/mondays-musings-beyond-the-three-vs-of-big-data-viscosity-and-virality/&quot;&gt;viscosity and virality&lt;/a&gt; were also contenders.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big data was now big, fast changing, complex, credible data that if mastered, would give you access to hidden value. Like the Gillette Fusion razor, more Vs might lead to a closer shave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/others/big-data-with-8-vs-min.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Now with 8 Vs: Image: © Serena Josh / Zaran Tech&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zarantech.com/blog/effective-way-handle-big-data/&quot;&gt;What is the effective way to handle big data?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big data after the hype&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today the big data hype is over. Fortunately, big data is now ‘business as usual’. The constant redefining of the phrase tracked its evolution, understanding and finally acceptance. New terms are rarely defined clearly to start with and big data was no exception. To be useful, it had to evolve. When you’re dealing with cutting edge technology, the odd knick is perhaps a small price to pay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/others/google-trends-big-data-time-series-min.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Image: © Google&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://trends.google.com/trends/explore?date=all&amp;amp;q=big%20data&quot;&gt;Google Trends big data time series&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the mid-2000’s, big data may have been hyped as a panacea: to save us from legacy systems, to tame the growing tsunami of data, and to predict the future. For some businesses, big data projects were an expensive solution without a problem that didn’t deliver value. For others, big data was a solution to specific operational, tactical or strategic problems that gave the business insights they couldn’t get any other way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big data today: harnessing the power of data to grow your business&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big data is now a mature tool that helps your business deliver on strategy. Businesses are better positioned today to take advantage of big data thanks to emerging technologies and disciplines including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New sources of data&lt;/strong&gt;: For example, everyday devices are connected to the internet and producing reams of new data. From internet-enabled vending machines to smart toasters, these devices make up the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.co.uk/article/internet-of-things-what-is-explained-iot&quot;&gt;Internet of Things or IoT&lt;/a&gt;. With the data devices generate, your business can remotely detect a part failing, monitor its delivery fleet, and save energy by dimming unused lighting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Faster, automated analysis:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sas.com/en_us/insights/analytics/machine-learning.html&quot;&gt;Machine learning&lt;/a&gt;  draws insights from big data so you can make decisions with less human input. Businesses are developing products in-house or using platforms like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/stevebanker/2019/09/03/big-data-big-insights-a-look-at-the-geotab-telematics-platform/#6beb60ce2442&quot;&gt;Geotab&lt;/a&gt;. This big data platform helps fleet managers remotely monitor the location and health of delivery vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cheaper data storage:&lt;/strong&gt; The cost of on-demand, remote data storage (or cloud storage) has dropped thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.techrepublic.com/article/microsoft-onedrive-most-used-cloud-storage-service-for-businesses-report/&quot;&gt;competition among cloud storage service providers&lt;/a&gt;. This makes it cheaper to store large volumes of data without investing in dedicated hardware. Businesses can choose between solutions offered by &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.google.com/solutions/big-data/&quot;&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oracle.com/big-data/&quot;&gt;Oracle&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://azure.microsoft.com/en-gb/solutions/big-data/&quot;&gt;Microsoft&lt;/a&gt;  and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big data is no longer on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gartner.com/en/research/methodologies/gartner-hype-cycle&quot;&gt;Gartner’s hype cycle&lt;/a&gt;  which tracks how technologies like big data evolve over time. Big data has become the norm. What hasn’t changed is the need for an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/why-your-business-needs-data-strategy-how-get-started-edafe-onerhime/&quot;&gt;effective data strategy&lt;/a&gt; for all business data. An offensive data strategy ensures big data is the right solution for your problem and delivers business value. A defensive data strategy reduces risks so big data is managed, protected and secured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When big data is the right solution, data strategy is as important as ever.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article owes a great deal to Amy Hupe’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://amyhupe.co.uk/articles/lets-write-more-blog-posts-an-experiment/&quot;&gt;#10MoreBlogPosts&lt;/a&gt; movement and my amazing beta readers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Amy_Hupe&quot;&gt;Amy Hupe&lt;/a&gt;: Senior Content Designer at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/government-digital-service&quot;&gt;GDS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/likeaword&quot;&gt;Ben Proctor&lt;/a&gt;: Communications and Community Development Specialist at &lt;a href=&quot;https://thesatorilab.com/&quot;&gt;Satori Lab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/NissaRamsay&quot;&gt;Nissa Ramsay&lt;/a&gt;: Founder of Think Social Tech&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Edafe Onerhime</name><email>hello@ekoner.com</email><uri>https://ekoner.com</uri></author><summary type="html">Big data: Will more Vs give you a closer shave?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/headers/header-black-man-shaving-min.jpg" /></entry><entry xml:lang="eng_GB"><title type="html">Why data strategy fails and how you can get it right</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/09/12/why-business-data-strategy-fails.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why data strategy fails and how you can get it right" /><published>2019-09-12T09:49:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-09-12T09:49:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/09/12/why-business-data-strategy-fails</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/09/12/why-business-data-strategy-fails.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/headers/header-diverse-meeting-min.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/headers/header-diverse-meeting-min.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Quote: Only 3% of companies' data meets basic data quality standards - here's how to get data strategy right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data is a valuable business asset, described as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/michelleevans1/2018/03/12/why-data-is-the-most-important-currency-used-in-commerce-today/#d61609754eb3&quot;&gt;the most important currency in commerce&lt;/a&gt; , yet &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2017/09/only-3-of-companies-data-meets-basic-quality-standards&quot;&gt;only 3% of companies’ data meets basic quality standards&lt;/a&gt;  and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.computerweekly.com/news/252467190/Data-breach-costs-on-the-rise-IBM-study-shows&quot;&gt;cost of data breaches to business is rising&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, I share how your business can avoid data strategy failure and how to get it right, leading to improved data to support business goals and reduce business risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 25 years I’ve worked with data, I found common patterns to why data strategies fail. Here are 3 key reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;1-you-dont-have-a-business-strategy&quot;&gt;1 You don’t have a business strategy&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A successful data strategy helps your business meet its goals and protects data from risks. To produce a data strategy, you need a business strategy. You need to understand the ecosystem the business operates in, who it serves, what it wants to achieve and how it plans to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this, you can create a data strategy that is offensive (ensures the business has the data and buy-in it needs to compete) and defensive (reduces risks to the business and complies with data regulations).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A successful data strategy needs a clear business strategy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;2-you-dont-know-your-blind-spots&quot;&gt;2 You don’t know your blind spots&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every business has existing systems in place for collecting, storing, and using data. These range from paper files to digital products to manage everything from accounting to social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An effective data strategy starts with a discovery - an audit of the products, processes, practices and skills used in your business. This helps to identify blind spots around data, as well as risks and hidden opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A successful data strategy starts with an audit.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;3-you-think-theres-a-quick-fix&quot;&gt;3 You think there’s a quick fix&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like a business strategy, a data strategy takes time to develop and implement. Rushing to develop and implement a data strategy without understanding the business, or bringing in a data specialist without any support can increase risks of blind spots, failed data initiatives and expensive software implementations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Implementing a successful data strategy is a gradual, long term process that’s everyone’s job - it isn’t enough to simply bring in a data specialist or rush to complete in a few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A successful data strategy needs a long term process.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;get-your-business-data-strategy-right&quot;&gt;Get your business data strategy right&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To develop and implement a data strategy that is both offensive and defensive, start with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Goals&lt;/strong&gt;: Use clear business goals to set the context for your data strategy and ensure it delivers what your business really cares about. In 2018,  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.affinitywater.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Affinity Water&lt;/a&gt; , the largest water-only supplier in the UK,  &lt;a href=&quot;https://stakeholder.affinitywater.co.uk/docs/Business_Plan/AFW-Appendix-C-Data-Strategy.pdf&quot;&gt;shared their data strategy&lt;/a&gt;  and how it aligns with business goals. Implementing a well developed data strategy reduces business risks and increases confidence in the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Buy-in&lt;/strong&gt;: A data strategy belongs in the boardroom and is accepted throughout the business.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.williamhill.com/&quot;&gt;William Hill&lt;/a&gt; , the world’s biggest bookmaker, found  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketingweek.com/crispin-nieboer-on-william-hills-data-driven-approach-to-customer-experience/&quot;&gt;wide acceptance key to delight&lt;/a&gt;  with their data-driven approach. With business-wide buy-in for a data strategy, it is likely to support business goals and be implemented successfully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Understanding&lt;/strong&gt;: A business is a complex system of people, processes and interactions. Understanding your business, especially blind spots and workarounds, is important when you develop and implement a data strategy. Skills like &lt;a href=&quot;https://thesystemsthinker.com/introduction-to-systems-thinking/&quot;&gt; systems thinking&lt;/a&gt;  can help your business spot the patterns and problems that could derail your data strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Audits&lt;/strong&gt;: Knowing who uses data, what for, and how is an important starting point in developing a successful data strategy. Audits can include a benchmark of &lt;a href=&quot;https://datacrossroads.nl/2018/12/16/data-management-maturity-models-a-comparative-analysis/&quot;&gt; data maturity&lt;/a&gt;  and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://databasic.io/en/culture/&quot;&gt; culture of data&lt;/a&gt;  in the business - the skills and confidence people have using data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Patience&lt;/strong&gt;: An effective data strategy is a gradual, long term process. The  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fca.org.uk/publication/corporate/fca-data-strategy.pdf&quot;&gt;Financial Conduct Authority data strategy&lt;/a&gt;  in 2013, for example, was followed up in 2014 with a  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fca.org.uk/publication/data/data-strategy-one-year-on.pdf&quot;&gt;reflection&lt;/a&gt;  on the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Iteration&lt;/strong&gt;: Using an iterative process like  &lt;a href=&quot;https://mitsloan.mit.edu/ideas-made-to-matter/design-thinking-explained&quot;&gt;Design thinking&lt;/a&gt;  can help your business develop a data strategy that has support and delivers by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fully understanding the problem&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exploring a wide range of solutions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Iterating through prototypes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Testing effectively&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Implementing successfully&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article owes a great deal to Amy Hupe’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://amyhupe.co.uk/articles/lets-write-more-blog-posts-an-experiment/&quot;&gt;#10MoreBlogPosts&lt;/a&gt;  movement and my amazing beta readers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Amy_Hupe&quot;&gt;Amy Hupe&lt;/a&gt; : Senior Content Designer at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/government-digital-service&quot;&gt;GDS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/likeaword&quot;&gt;Ben Proctor&lt;/a&gt; : Communications and Community Development Specialist at &lt;a href=&quot;https://thesatorilab.com/&quot;&gt;Satori Lab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/laurencurrie/&quot;&gt;Lauren Currie OBE&lt;/a&gt; : Managing Director of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/company/nobl-collective/&quot;&gt;NOBL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Edafe Onerhime</name><email>hello@ekoner.com</email><uri>https://ekoner.com</uri></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/headers/header-diverse-meeting-min.jpg" /></entry><entry xml:lang="eng_GB"><title type="html">Why your business needs a data strategy and how to get started</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/09/01/why-your-business-needs-a-data-strategy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why your business needs a data strategy and how to get started" /><published>2019-09-01T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-09-01T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/09/01/why-your-business-needs-a-data-strategy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/09/01/why-your-business-needs-a-data-strategy.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/headers/header-diverse-boardroom-min.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/headers/header-diverse-boardroom-min.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Quote: A data strategy belongs in the board room&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses have always run on data, from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sumer#Language_and_writing&quot;&gt;5,000 year old Sumerian trade on clay tablets&lt;/a&gt; to today’s silicon-driven &lt;a href=&quot;https://eiuperspectives.economist.com/sites/default/files/Artificial_intelligence_in_the_real_world_1.pdf&quot;&gt;artificial intelligence algorithms&lt;/a&gt;, data is at the heart of practically every business decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data is used everywhere in your business and in every team.  Successful businesses use data to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deliver marketing strategy by creating market segments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Help sales predict which customers will buy what products and when&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Monitor customer satisfaction in customer services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Better data leads to better decisions which creates competitive advantage. Here I’ll explain why you need a data strategy and how to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2007/09/demystifying-strategy-the-what&quot;&gt;a good business strategy is a roadmap&lt;/a&gt; to creating competitive advantage, a data strategy is roadmap to how your business will get, store, use and protect data to meet its goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An effective &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2017/05/whats-your-data-strategy&quot;&gt;data strategy&lt;/a&gt; is both defensive (protect, update and keep data accurate) and offensive (use data to compete, be productive and make a profit).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some businesses, data strategy is part of the IT plan. This is business risk. Positioning data as part of technology misses the value of &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.informatica.com/2015/11/23/data-strategic-asset/#fbid=4WO3pGQ8V0S&quot;&gt;data as a strategic asset&lt;/a&gt;.  Data brings both risks (and the need for a defensive data strategy) and benefits (which needs an offensive data strategy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/quotes/quote-data-is-a-strategic-asset-min.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/quotes/quote-data-is-a-strategic-asset-min.png&quot; alt=&quot;Quote: Data is a strategic asset&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without an effective defensive data strategy, your business risks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fines for noncompliance&lt;/strong&gt;: If your business collects, uses or manages information about people, it may also need to comply with regulations like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://gdpr.eu/&quot;&gt;General Data Protection Regulation&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;GDPR&lt;/strong&gt;)  or the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hhs.gov/hipaa/for-professionals/privacy/laws-regulations/index.html&quot;&gt;Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;HIPAA&lt;/strong&gt;). GDPR fines are intentionally painful for businesses, large and small. Fines are up to €10 million, or up to 2% of the worldwide revenue for the previous financial year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Poor decision-making&lt;/strong&gt;: Flawed or incomplete data can lead to employees making decisions that hurt a business, like accounting errors because customer data is duplicated, or over-spending because stock levels are wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hidden costs&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2016/09/bad-data-costs-the-u-s-3-trillion-per-year&quot;&gt;Poor data leads to expensive mistakes&lt;/a&gt; which cause partners, suppliers and customers to lose trust in a business. Employees that have to workaround poor data are less productive, customers are impacted when orders are sent to the wrong address and suppliers become irate when invoices are paid late.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Negative media coverage&lt;/strong&gt;: There’s also a risk of unwanted media attention when serious mistakes are made, like sending correspondence to a deceased person, or mistakes in the companies financial reports.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With an effective offensive data strategy, your business can compete with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A central view of information&lt;/strong&gt;: It’s likely your business uses a mix of products to manage accounting and customers, customer communication channels like social media and mailing lists. Each of these products stores information about customers, suppliers, sales, and more. With a good data strategy, you can have a central view of customers, suppliers and other important information. This central view becomes your business’s single source of truth.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Business-wide buy-in&lt;/strong&gt;: Making a data strategy a purely IT effort can lead to a lack of buy-in from other areas of your business. In IT, data becomes a technology problem. In the boardroom, data becomes everyone’s  responsibility.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Business strategy support&lt;/strong&gt;:  Your data strategy supports your business strategy with data (facts, statistics, numbers)  to test your vision, understand your networks, refine your mission and deliver your goals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/quotes/quote-data-strategy-min.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/quotes/quote-data-strategy-min.png&quot; alt=&quot;Quote: A data strategy is a business-wide plan for competing, with data&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A data strategy is a business-wide plan for competing, with data&lt;/strong&gt;.  A data strategy belongs in the board room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get started with a data strategy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Treat data as an asset aligned with your business strategy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bring ownership of business data to the boardroom&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Balance defensive and offensive data strategy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In my next article&lt;/strong&gt;, I share why data strategy fails and how you can get it right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you to my amazing beta readers and content wranglers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Amy_Hupe&quot;&gt;Amy Hupe&lt;/a&gt;: Senior Content Designer at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/government-digital-service&quot;&gt;GDS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/likeaword&quot;&gt;Ben Proctor&lt;/a&gt;: Communications and Community Development Specialist at &lt;a href=&quot;https://thesatorilab.com&quot;&gt;Satori Lab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/reinikainen&quot;&gt;Esko Reinikainen&lt;/a&gt;: Organisational Development Specialist at &lt;a href=&quot;https://thesatorilab.com&quot;&gt;Satori Labs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Shi&quot;&gt;Shi Blank&lt;/a&gt;: Feral Game Developer at &lt;a href=&quot;http://wetgenes.com/welcome&quot;&gt;Wet Genes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Edafe Onerhime</name><email>hello@ekoner.com</email><uri>https://ekoner.com</uri></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/headers/header-diverse-boardroom-min.jpg" /></entry></feed>